hey guys hey going in this video I'm
going to be showing you how to use CSS
grid in order to create a basic layout
just like this for your web projects so
this video is intended for people who
are just starting out using CSS grid and
basically I'm going to be covering most
of the main features so that you can get
started and of course start implementing
a CSS grid for your own web projects so
this right here is the basic layouts we
have a header we have some content
sections and we have of course the
footer so basically this layout is going
to support this right here so this sort
of two column content layout as well as
a three column content layout just like
this so there's a small change in the
CSS in order to transform this right
here into this right here so of course
you can choose which one suits your
scenario better so anyway let's go
inside this HTML file right here we're
gonna start from scratch to create that
layout so inside the text editor it
looks something like this it is a plain
HTML skeleton so first to get started we
need to of course specify HTML so let's
create a container so a div with a class
of container for the actual grid
container so then inside the CSS let's
just firstly target the body and set a
margin of zero to remove the default
margin this way I can say container so
tighter the class of container and say
width and make this 100 review port week
and for the height we can say 100 and
viewport height and of course the
combination of these three means that
the container is going to take up the
entire width and height of the web page
so now saving this and refreshing inside
the dev tools if I was to hover over the
container we can see it spans the entire
width and the height of the available
viewing area I'm also just going to go
back inside here and specify some font
styling
to make things easier for us to read so
font-family let's make this quick sand
with sand sir and for the font weight
let's make this bold and also a font
size of something like 20 pixels so now
that is all set so we can now move on to
actually using a CSS grid so for this we
need to firstly specify that our
container is gonna be a grid or a grid
container for this we can say display
and make this grid so now we are ready
to start adding some grid items or at
least specify our layer so now I just
want to go back to the previous layout
right here because I now of course our
grid right here is ready to actually be
used we need to specify the amount of
columns and the amount of rows and also
their sizes for our base layer that's
basically how grid works you've got this
base grid layer of rows and columns in
the background and then once your layout
is complete you can say that certain
elements are going to span multiple rows
or multiple columns or even a
combination of the two so with that
being said let's go back to this example
and analyze and take a look at our
columns and rows for this layer as we
can see here in terms of rows we've got
four rows in total we've got one row
we've got two rows three rows and then
four rows okay even though this content
right here is spanning multiple rows we
still consider this to have a total of 4
rows 1 2 3 and then 4 in terms of
columns this actually has three columns
even though two are visible we've got
one we've got two and we've got three
that's easier to explain on this example
right here with the three column layer
one two and three so with that being
said this is a four by three layer
which means we can specify this in the
CSS for our example or this right here
so in the CSS let's hop inside the
container and we're gonna say down here
grid template columns and this right
here lets us specify the amount of
columns and also their sizes so we're
going to say 1 FR 1 FR and then 1 FR so
here we're specifying three columns
since we have three values separated by
a space and the width of those columns
is one fraction of the total remaining
space so basically we've got three
evenly spaced columns which are going to
shrink in size as we shrink our browser
because it is a fraction of the
available space okay and that is all for
the columns if you wanted to simplify
this declaration you could instead save
repeats then 3 and then your value so 1
fr and basically doing this is the exact
same as saying what if I wanna fire and
then one afar so now we can specify the
amount of rows for this we're gonna say
grid template rows in a very similar way
and for this it's going to be a bit more
complicated but not too much
so let's go back in the example and we
can see right here of course got the 4
rows the header row is 50 pixels in
height ok these two right here are gonna
be the same height but they're gonna be
once again a fraction of the available
space and the bottom one here is 100
pixels fixed so essentially the top and
the and the actual bottom rows are going
to be fixed heights of 50 and 100 pixels
and these two are gonna be a fraction of
the left or remaining space which means
if I was to shrink this browser height
we can see that only the two middle rows
are changing their height the header and
footer remain fixed so for this let's go
back inside here
we're going to say 50 pixels for the
first row and then one fr or one fr and
then 100 pixels for the bottom row of
course these two are absolutes and these
two are fractional and they can shrink
if they need to when the browser resizes
so now we've specified the columns and
the rows I can save this and then
refresh the browser inside the dev tools
if I was to hover over the container we
can see that Chrome gives us a
representation of our layer of course we
can see we have all of our rows and
columns working perfectly fine so now we
can move on to specifying a gap between
each one of our areas here so for this
it is very straightforward we can simply
say gap and make these 10 pixels for
example saving this and refreshing gives
us this right here of course a 10 pixels
gap excluding the edges of the container
if you wanted to add a 10 pixels gap on
the edges this can be done using padding
and then box-sizing let's go back inside
here and do that so we can say paddle
make this 10 pixels the same as the
actual gap size and box sizing our
border box to contain the padding as
being part of the total width of the
container let's save this and now we
have this right here which is identical
to our container in both of these two
examples so now essentially we are
finished with the container I do want to
go back inside here and just add a new
rule set for container and then do so
I'm gonna say padding here and make
these 10 pixels and say border at 1
pixel solid and then a black so now
essentially every great item so header
and all the content and the footer each
one of those divs are gonna have a
border I'm sorry I can actually see how
they look and how many rows and columns
they span so now so now let's move on to
creating the header we can make a new
div with a
I'll slap it on and just say head up as
the content so now if I save this and
refresh we can see that the header is
taking up a single column and a single
row in terms of its size okay so to make
the head a spend the remaining rows so
row number sorry our column so column
number two and column number three this
can be done using the grid column start
and the grid column end properties so
let's go inside here and I'm gonna say
for the class file header reads poem
start and make this one and say grids
column end and make this four
so to explain what the one and the four
means basically here you're specifying
the grid line number so a grid line is
basically alliance between your rows and
your columns so I'm gonna be showing you
what that means right now so in the
browser as we can see here we've got a
total of four grid lines on the
horizontal sorry on the vertical axis we
have right here at the edge this is grid
line number one we then have grid line
number two right here and then grid line
number three just about here and then
line number four just about here okay
that's very important to understand when
it comes to making your items span
multiple rows or multiple columns the
same goes for the horizontal axis okay
we of course have grid line number one
just up here okay number two and then of
course number three number four and then
number five just down here so that is
what our main bar grid lines so when I
specify a grid column start at one and
end before I mean that the header is
gonna start at number one add fish
number four so now saving this and
refreshing gives us this right here for
further clarification if I make this
grid column end
se3 save this and refresh we can see now
it goes to 3 so 1 2 and then 3
ok so perfect so let's just set this
back to be 4 yeah so now we can move on
to creating the content right here so
this is where I'm gonna I'm gonna first
show you how to do these two columns for
this content number 1 and then after
that I'll be showing you how to change
that so it actually expands so I so
actually spans two rows and then two
columns just like this one okay so back
inside here let's specify our two more
elements for each one of those content
areas so I can say right here a class of
content - large and we can say right
here content number one and make this a
and then make this B so with this right
here if I save this and refresh we can
see it is successfully flowed across to
the second row and the actual items
themselves are once again taking up a
single piece of area so single row in a
single column okay so now we're gonna
simply in a very similar way to the
header
we're gonna make these to span multiple
rows so you may have guessed we're going
to be using the grid row start and the
grid row ends to achieve that let's
target the content large class and make
this breed a row start we can make it
start of course at number two and a grid
the row ends and this time I'm going to
be using span - so basically span - is
an alternative to specifying an actual
grid line number and let's just save
this and refresh we can see we get this
result right here so of course the grid
row start was two so this second grid
line right here and we used span so when
I said span - it basically means we're
going to start here
then span two lines of course span we
have line number three right here and
then line that before just down here so
started two and then span two gives us
this result but here of course as an
alternative I could simply just say fall
instead of using the span to it works
the exact same way it saved this refresh
and of course we get no different so
I'll just set this back to being span
two so now if we want to make this so
this single content our spans also you
know this second column here just like
this one
this can be done quite easily I'm just
going to be removing this second content
item and making this simply content
number one so now we can go inside here
and we can also say grid column start
and make this one and then grids column
end and make this three so essentially
we're combining both the grid row and
the greedy column so now I'll save this
and refresh and we can see right here we
start at column number one and we finish
at column number three right here and of
course the row spanning is still in
effect so now we get this large box
spanning multiple rows and then multiple
columns so now moving on to the tiny
boxes on the right side here this is
going to be very straightforward we're
gonna simply create two more elements so
content small and also content small
adjust here and for this we can say
content number two and then content
number three save this and of course
these ones also flow naturally so
they're in the correct spot and that is
awfully small content items so for the
foot out it's gonna work in the same way
as they head out but I'm gonna be
showing you a different way to specify
your column spans so back inside here
let's create the element for the footer
so with their class of
just like this and this CSS rule says
four footer is gonna say greet - Poland
and we're gonna say one forward slash
and then spam to read so for this this
is basically just shorthand for saying
grid column starts at one and grid
column end at span three so basically
this right here is the equivalent to
this right here you separate your start
and your end with a forward slash
so now saving this and refreshing is
gonna give us this result right here
exactly what we want I might just go
back and make this actually save footer
so one last thing I want to show you is
going to be the combination of the grid
templates on the container in a very
similar way as we did right here so for
this we can simply say grid template and
we're going to firstly specify the row
so basically this guy right here then a
forward slash and then say repeats three
1fr just like this so now this right
here in a similar way to this one this
is the exact same as saying this right
here it is simply just a shorthand so
now getting rid of this is going to give
us the exact same result let's save this
and refresh and we can see about he of
course we get the same result and that's
how to create a basic layer from scratch
using CSS grid thanks for watching guys
and I'll see you later